Guide to the Ann Imbrie Papers, 1950-2006
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Ann Imbrie Papers
1950-2006
Imbrie, Ann E. (Ann Elizabeth)
3.8 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to Imbrie's work as a writer and professor of English. There is some additional material relating to her personal life. Of particular note are Imbrie's letters home from Smith College and the University of North Carolina, letters from her friend John M. Randall while he was serving in Vietnam, and Imbrie's research material and drafts for Spoken in Darkness.
Biographical Note
Ann E. Imbrie, daughter of Rev. Greer S. Imbrie and Julia Ann McCorkle, joined the Vassar College English Department in 1979. She chaired the department from 1995-2001 and was named the Mary Augusta Scott Professor of English. Before coming to Vassar, Imbrie earned her B.A. from Smith College (1972) and her M.A. and Ph.D. from the University of North Carolina (1974 and 1979). Her areas of specialty were Renaissance literature, creative fiction and non-fiction. She published many articles and reviews and in 1993 released Spoken in Darkness., a mix of memoir and fiction centered on the murder of a childhood friend.
Imbrie died 20 May 2006 from complications arising from treatment of metastatic melanoma.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, manuscripts, and teaching materials relating to Imbrie's work as a writer and professor of English. There is some additional material relating to her personal life. Of particular note are Imbrie's letters home from Smith College and the University of North Carolina, letters from her friend John M. Randall while he was serving in Vietnam, and Imbrie's research material and drafts for Spoken in Darkness.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College. Department of English
Subjects:
Women authors; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Personal narratives, American; Women teachers
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, July 2009.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paul Russell, August 2007.
Series List
- Series I. Biography
- Series II. Correspondence
- Series III. Writings
- Series IV. Teaching Material
Container List
- SERIES I. Biography
  - Birth information, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Resumes (Box 1)
  - News Clippings (Box 1)
  - Poetry and journal entries, ca. 1972-1982 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Journal fragment, Oct 1984 (Box 1)
  - Notes, correspondence and poetry (Box 1)
  - High school awards (Box 1)
  - High school yearbook, 1968 (Box 1)
  - High school reunion booklet, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous school material, ca. 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - Medical logs, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - "All of Me: the Letters of Greer S. Imbrie to Julia Ann McCorkle" (Box 1)
  - Greer Imbrie’s sermons (Box 1)
  - "Poems written in Honor of Ann Imbrie, 1964-1967" (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- SERIES II. Correspondence
  - Imbrie to family from Smith College, 1968-1972; (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Imbrie to family from University of North Carolina, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Brimecombe, Jerry David, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Caschetta, Mary Beth, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Gelvin, Elizabeth, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Greenberg, Bob, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Imbrie, Charity, 1968-1969, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Imbrie, Greer, 1980-1994 (Box 1)
  - Imbrie, Julia, 1968-2001 (Box 1)
  - Imbrie, Katy, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Leland, John, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Mallon, Tom, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Misuraca, Danny, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Nichols, Judy, 1995, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Rahdert, George, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Rottnek, Matt, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Russell, Paul, 2004-2006 (Box 1)
  - Wright, Glenn "Pat,", ca. 1973-1994 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous personal, 1968-2003, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous professional, 1977-1994 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous from students, 1981-1998 (Box 4)
- SERIES III. Writings
  - Spoken in Darkness
    - Proposal (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with the Law Offices of Bogle and Gates (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with publishers and contracts, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Royalties (Box 1)
    - Bloomsbury promotional material, ca. 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Advance excerpts (Box 1)
    - Book cover (Box 1)
    - Book cover, (mounted) (Box 4)
    - Reviews and articles, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Reader correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Screenplay by Hunter Hill and Perry Moore (Box 1)
    - Screenplay by Kate Robin, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Script for play by Frances Gray (Box 1)
    - Posters for the Frances Gray / Dominic Druce play, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Poster for the Frances Gray / Dominic Druce play, 1997; (mounted) (Box 4)
    - "A Local Habitation and a Name: The Writer in the Public Library," Wood County Library talk, 1993 (Box 1)
    - "Habitation of the Heart" (Box 1)
    - Women's Studies class handout (Box 1)
    - Research material, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Audio tapes (Box 2)
    - Drafts, (9 folders) (Box 2)
  - Other Writings
    - "Animals, Ink: An Anthology of Animal Poems, 1530-2000" (edited by Imbrie and Kaitlin Harvie, VC 2005) (Box 2)
    - "The Art of The Arte of Angling, 1577," The American Fly Fisher, Fall 1983 (Box 2)
    - "The Color Line" (Box 2)
    - Coming to Terms: A Writer's Life with Dogs, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - "The D.C. Shuffle" (Box 2)
    - "Goose Trees and Burbots: Richard Franck's Northern Memoirs," The American Fly Fisher, Winter 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Gossip", (4 drafts) (Box 2)
    - "Literary Form and Literary Value in Thomas Browne's Urne-Buriall" (Box 2)
    - "The Names of Doon: A Memoir" (Box 2)
    - On Foot Against Pegasus: Nonfiction Forms in the Later English Renaissance, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - "'Playing Legerdemaine with the Scripture': Parodic Sermons in The Fairie Queene," English Literary Renaissance, Spring 1987 (Box 2)
    - "The Poker Game" (Box 2)
    - "'Redeeming Nature': A Symbolic Interpretation of King Lear" (Box 2)
    - "Renaissance Genre Theory and the Form of Nonfiction Prose" (Box 2)
    - "Renaissance London: A Modern Tourist's Guide", (2 drafts) (Box 3)
    - "Robert Burton: A Reference Guide" (Box 3)
    - "Serendipity" (Box 3)
    - Sir Thomas Browne and Robert Burton: A Reference Guide (with Dennis Donovan and Magaretha G. Hartley Herman) Boston: G.K. Hall, 1981; (bound volume) (Box 3)
    - Studies in 'The Other Harmony': Prose Genres in the Later English Renaissance, (dissertation, bound volume) (Box 3)
    - Tapestries of Paradise, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - "Telling Errors/Righting Lives: Biography on the Margins" (Box 3)
    - "To Take Your Heart Away" (Box 3)
    - Transcendence in the Poetry of Wallace Stevens, (thesis, bound volume) (Box 3)
    - "Translation" (Box 3)
    - "Tulips", (2 drafts) (Box 3)
    - "'Unaccommodated man': Conditions of Existence in King Lear" (Box 3)
    - "What Shalimar Knew: Toni Morrison's Song of Solomon as a Pastoral Novel," College English, Sep 1993 (Box 3)
    - "When the Stars Begin to Fall" (Box 3)
    - "Whose Story is this Anyway" (Box 3)
    - "'Wit's Camelion': The Feminine Reader in Elizabeth Grimston's Miscelanea", (2 drafts) (Box 3)
    - "Words Become Us," Vassar Quarterly, Winter 1999 (Box 3)
    - "A Writer in the Public Library, Ohio Libraries, Winter 1994 (Box 3)
    - Poetry notebook, ca. 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - Poetry, ca. 1973 (Box 3)
    - Early poem labeled "The beginning of a career…" (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous poetry and notes (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous book reviews (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Smith College papers, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Fragments (Box 3)
- SERIES IV. Teaching Material
  - Eng 20 (Box 3)
  - Eng 101 (Box 3)
  - Eng 105 (Box 3)
  - Eng 106 (Box 3)
  - Eng 230 (Box 3)
  - Eng 231 (Box 3)
  - Eng 367 (Box 3)
  - Eng 368 (Box 3)
  - 19th Century (Box 3)
  - 18th Century (Box 3)
  - Shakespeare (Box 3)
  - Spenser (Box 3)
  - Grammar (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)